<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Laus pediculi: or An apologeticall speech, directed to the vvorshipfull masters and vvardens of Beggars Hall. Written in Latine by the learned Daniel Heinsius. And from thence translated into English by Iames Guitard, Gentleman</title>
            <title>Laus pediculi. English</title>
            <author>Heinsius, Daniel, 1580-1655.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1634</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 25 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02893</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13038</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103932</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839674</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839674</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4115</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02893)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4115)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 889:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Laus pediculi: or An apologeticall speech, directed to the vvorshipfull masters and vvardens of Beggars Hall. Written in Latine by the learned Daniel Heinsius. And from thence translated into English by Iames Guitard, Gentleman</title>
                  <title>Laus pediculi. English</title>
                  <author>Heinsius, Daniel, 1580-1655.</author>
                  <author>Guitard, James.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 21, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Tho. Harper,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1634.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lice --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4115:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4115:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Laus Pediculi</hi>: OR AN APOLOGETICALL SPEECH, Directed to the VVorſhipfull Maſters and VVardens of Beggars HALL.</p>
            <p>Written in Latine by the learned DANIEL HEINSIUS.</p>
            <p>And from thence tranſlated into Engliſh by IAMES GVITARD, Gentleman.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by THO. HARPER. 1634.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:4115:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4115:2"/>
            <head>TO THE HONORABLE HENRY, Lord CARY, Baron of <hi>Leppington,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>IS confeſt, that Authors ſhould bee as proper in their Dedication, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite in their expreſsion. Nor know J which is the greater felicity. For the latter, let but the Cenſurer become a Reader, and J thinke the Worke will vindicate it ſelfe; though the name of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Compoſer may be enough. The
<pb facs="tcp:4115:3"/>
former J muſt defend: whether the Preſent be according to the Preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee, honorable; the Author would make a man beleeve it ſo: and if it be not, yet let the plea bee heard a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore condemnatory ſentence. Howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, let me not be mistooke; my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication is in the abſtract, the ſtrein of wit. Let Poets (for J count this Pamphlet but poeticall proſe) bee in the ſame degree of priviledge with Painters. Jt undervalueth not the Pencill of the herein admirable, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drian Brower,</hi> that his drawghts be but revelling Beggars and drunken Bores: <hi>Stultitiam ſimulare loco ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pientia ſummaeſt.</hi> So the lively ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsion of naturall rudeneſſe, to the eye of apprehenſive curioſity, may ſeeme the height of artificiall feat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.
<pb facs="tcp:4115:3"/>
My Lord, you have a tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency above others from Nature and Fortune. Nor can ſuch a qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified Spirit affect but tranſcendent objects: among which I ſuppoſe this to be ſuch Chymiſtry of conceit, as can extract a ſpecious diſcourſe, not from a barren but a contrary ſubject. This doth the Tranſlator preſent to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with himſelfe,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>To your Lordſhip in all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion of ſervice,</hi> I. G.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:4115:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:4115:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Laus Pediculi:</hi> Directed to the VVorſhipfull Maſters and Wardens of Beggars HALL.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Aldermen Canters,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Ancient VVriters have delivered, that O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion is <hi>Sacer morbus,</hi> which is of that power, that on whomſoever it lightly breatheth, it doth (as it were) fetter him with chaynes, and doth not ſuffer his eyes never ſo little to peep towards the dawning truth. But this is chiefly to be deplored, that having once taken poſſeſſion of the judgement, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the welfare of mankinde doth depend, it commandeth the ſuffrages and voyces, and ſwayeth on that which is foreſtalled
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:4115:5"/>
with fancy. Nay, in troth, ſhee her ſelfe doth execute the place of judicature. Who is ſo forlorne of ſenſe, as not to confeſſe that this is apparant in our defendants cauſe? This ſame <hi>Louce,</hi> a creature of fame, and common note, mans familiar gueſt, &amp; retainer, born and bred of him, his home-batled nurſling, and cheriſhed with the warmth of the ſame harth, borne to the communion of Fortune, &amp; tutelar depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency, &amp; allied in the ſacred tie of any other domeſtick relation: yea, your ever truſty companion ſuffers under the tyrannicall oppreſſion of men, and is made by them as contemptibly infamous as they can: and is not only baniſht from ſea and land, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo is moſt barbarouſly expelled and eje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted from the body of man, which is his onely ſeate of life and maintenance. The cauſe whereof being demanded, it will bee found no other but meerely Opinion. The which to have fully driven out of the minde, I thinke it much avayling to the ſafety of this defendant, whom the more earneſtly to commend unto you, I thinke
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:4115:5"/>
it ſufficient to notifie unto you his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable properties. Firſt of all, they ſay the very name is infamous, <hi>heaven help us!</hi> which is derived from the moſt faſhiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble part of the body (as they themſelves dare not deny:) firſt men did call him <hi>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem</hi> or foot; afterwards by a loving and flattering appellation they called him <hi>pedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culum,</hi> with as honeſt a name as eyther <hi>Oe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dipus</hi> or <hi>Polypus,</hi> which have the ſame E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timology. See therefore, and thoroughly view the force of Opinion; no man thinks it ugly to ſay <hi>pediculorum montem, populos pediculos, pediculorum agrum, ſive flumen,</hi> a hill of Lice, a nation of Lice, a field and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of Lice, that I meddle not with the Lice of leaues and fruites. Although the Romans would not ſee them want illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and magnificent names, as when they called them Serpents, or creepers, and <hi>Sex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upedes</hi> or ſixfooted creatures; Yet the Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians much leſſe would; which amongſt other names haue giuen him one from the very ſhop of reaſon, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the brayne of man. The Hebrewes haue named him
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:4115:6"/>
alſo from a powerfull word <hi>canan,</hi> which ſignifies with them to lay a foundation, (from whence <hi>can,</hi> a pedeſtall, foot, or foundation;) eyther becauſe they are the foundation, of greater animals, or elſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are ſupported of many feet, as upon a baſis. Therefore they are called <hi>cinnim,</hi> by that moſt ancient nation. The Greeke Septuagint called them <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, not as being other cattell (which we euer dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med) but from their compaſſe, becauſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is as much to ſay, as little or ſmall. Whence the Chaldeans alſo from their pinched and conciſed body called them <hi>cimlin,</hi> and the Arabians <hi>camla:</hi> meaning this ſelfe ſame creature. Nor neede any one bee aſhamed heereof, ſeeing valour eyther excuſeth or commendeth the thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and contractedneſſe of their body, which alſo euery one admires in Piſmires, unto whom the Ancients do aſcribe migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty wiſedome. Nor doe our clients alſo when they fall upon mans fleſh, behave themſelves leſſe valiantly, as that every one deſerve the ſame co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendation which
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:4115:6"/>
the Prince of Poets gives to that great Hero.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Tydeus was but of ſtature ſmall,</l>
               <l>Yet of his warlicke hands was tall.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Although our defendant thinks it doth not concerne him at all, by what names he is ſtiled: Which excellent humour of indifferency, doubtleſſe he tooke from the Stoicks, when hee lived heeretofore gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing in their beards and brows. Further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, whereas both Orators and Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers doe fetch the roote and originall of prayſe from ones native ſoyle; (which <hi>Plato</hi> approoves of alſo in his <hi>Menexenus,</hi> our Sparke was borne neyther at <hi>Athens,</hi> nor <hi>Rome</hi>; which Cities have beene prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and celebrated by great Orators, even untill the hearers eares were cloyed. The native ſoile of the Louce is Man; whoſe worth and prerogative to blazen, were but a ſilly and idle enterprize: who as hee is onely endued with Reaſon, ſo hath alſo Reaſon impallaced in his loftieſt and moſt topping part, to wit, the head. And this hath our Client made choyce of deſerved<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:4115:7"/>
as a caſtle and fort of great importance. Heere he is bred, heere he is brought up, heere his eſtate and mayntenance ſubſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth; of this is he the native inhabitant and free deniſon, ſcorning the lower regions, and as ancient Poets ſayd prettily,
<q>
                  <l>There is no greater good</l>
                  <l>Then a good neighbourhood.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>He hath the minde, hee hath the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, he hath prudence and wiſedome for his neighbours, and almoſt familiars, ſo that the aſſe, which hath the leaſt por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of theſe, a dull and lumpiſh creature, only knows not what it is to have a Louce, as it is commonly beleeved. On the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, theſe moſt prudent mortall creatures doe beſides man, the divine and truely chiefeſt creature, purſue alſo moſt eagerly the dog and the nightingale, whom they perceive to be of moſt excellent wit, that it might be verified what firſt <hi>Homer,</hi> and then <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> have ſayd,
<q>Like will to like.</q>
            </p>
            <p>It was a happineſſe of wit that made the Ancients to ſirname <hi>Plato</hi> divine, whoſe
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:4115:7"/>
Lice are become a Proverbe. To omit <hi>Pherycides,</hi> and <hi>Alcman,</hi> whoſe tickling ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herents theſe were to the laſt gaſpe. The chiefe gentry of them are imparked in the head.</p>
            <q>
               <l>The meaner yeamondry</l>
               <l>Doe billet ſcatteringly.</l>
            </q>
            <p>For they doe almoſt every where ſend their colonies and make plantations in the apparell, in the eyebrowes, in the beard; though not all of the ſame kind, and form. If you looke after the antiquity of their pedegree, you muſt continue it beyond <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>richteus</hi> and <hi>Cecrops,</hi> even unto the times of <hi>Deucalion.</hi> For as ſoone as the ſtones waxe warme with humane breath, our Client ſucceeded that warmth; who ever ſince hath judged to bee beſt for him, to keepe himſelfe out of the cold as much as he can. Man therefore is borne of ſtone, but the Lice are borne of Man. So much the nobler in his originall, as a man is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bler then a ſtone. <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> would have them bred of the fleſh, but <hi>Theophraſtus</hi> of the blood, both the moſt noble and prime
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:4115:8"/>
parts of the body, (as every one knoweth.) And they ſay they are born by corruption. Cruell Authors! thinking to batter down innocency by this engine. Suffer not (my Canting Lords) that before your Barre, ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance ſhould prejudice and diſtreſſe the cauſe of this defendant, againſt the trueth. For if they goe on ſo, it will bee the ſame caſe with man, the ſame caſe with all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther living creatures. For as from the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of bloud is ſperme, ſo from the corruption of ſperme both man and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther living are bred. What more beautifull then a Peacocke? it is borne from an egge corrupted. What is more prudent then the Bee? what more cleanly? what more needfull in the world? yet is borne from the corruption of an Oxe For Nature doth beget nothing of another, but ſo, as that ſomething is corrupted; and by this way doth preſerve all things. Whereupon <hi>Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thagoras</hi> excellently ſayd that nothing dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, but all things in this world are onely changed. Yea, on the contrary (ſo heavens proſper me) you will ſay, it is wonderfully
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:4115:8"/>
come to paſſe, that after the one and the ſame maner, two famouſeſt creatures are created, the Louce and the Phenix; one from his parents aſhes; the other of a Nit; as not without cauſe the moſt eminent Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors doe conjoyne and compare the ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall of both. If you beleeve <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> that there proceedeth nothing from a Nit, then you will make the firſt authour of a Louce, the deputy of Deity, I meane, The Vniverſall heat; which the Arabes, not without cauſe, have called, The Creator; unto which, when this creature is to bee procreated, the naturall heat is adioyned. Now if you ſearch into his education; as ſoone as the Louce enters into the Leaſe of his life, he is inſtituted in thoſe arts &amp; diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plines, which he thinketh are moſt condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing and importing for his courſe of life: he learneth not Swimming, becauſe he liveth upon the continent; nor learning and ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, in that he ſeeth theſe doe no wayes avayle their teachers, for the moſt part, unto the attayning of vertue. Therefore being moſt an end buſied in husbandry
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:4115:9"/>
and domeſtique affaires, all the ſpare time remayning from the exerciſe and care of feeding, it beſtoweth on contemplation, and reſt: and herein liveth moſt of all like the Gods; whom <hi>Homer</hi> giveth this Epithete of <hi>Eaſie Livers:</hi> for hee doth not ſeeke his forrage, but hath his victuals in a cubbord, ready for his mouth; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever he turnes himſelfe hee fals to what is afore him, without any ſervicing. To omit another thing which is common to them with <hi>Homers</hi> Deities,
<q>
                  <l>On bread they do not feed,</l>
                  <l>Nor drink what Grapes do bleed.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>They do not manure or till the ground, but gently twich and prick mans fleſh. If you demand the conſtitution of their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, it doth almoſt eſcape the eye-ſight. Curious Nature hath woven together their members with ſuch exceeding fine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, as that they fall under the intellect, and are almoſt inviſible; wherein they are of affinity with incorporeall things, who by their excellency, are above the ſenſes, being to bee apprehended only by
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:4115:9"/>
reaſon. And alſo with the atomes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with <hi>Leucippus</hi> in his contemplative ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chitecture, <hi>Democritus,</hi> and <hi>Epicure</hi> Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penter-like, made the world off, which therefore a Roman Poet of the Retinue of Epicures did call <hi>The materiall bodies, The firſt bodies, The principles, The ſeeds of things,</hi> and <hi>The matter.</hi> But eſpecially <hi>Acarus</hi> or the Hand-worme, known unto <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> hath this affinity with atomes, which hath almoſt got the ſame name; howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of the ſame ſignification: for it can neither bee divided, nor cleft, nor ſcarce ſeene: which if it ſhould offer it ſelfe to the eye, and every particular member to be viewed: I would make you preſently ſee firſt the Lice, and alſo the concurrence of hooked, rough, and ſmooth Atomes. Now it hath made choice of a quiet and and retired courſe of life, not fluttering as birds do, nor skip-hopping as a flea, but according to the dignity of his life, ſtable, and ſtill: hee walketh with a ſlow, and gravely compoſed gate: nor doth he ſeem to imbrace any point of Philoſophy more
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:4115:10"/>
than the Pythagorean ſilence; for nothing diſturbeth more the intentiveneſſe of the minde, than a hurry, and a buſtling noyſe: which intentiveneſſe being continuall, it ſurmounts the bliſſe of man. Neither is hee altogether idle, and abſtayning from action, for hee is alwayes feaſting and cramming. <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſaid well, that Man is a ſociable creature, and therefore the foundation, and ground of a Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth. The which no man (unleſſe hee never ſaw him) but knoweth may as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinently be ſaid of this our client: for they live in familiar ſociety one with another, and with man alſo: it is not ſo eaſily judged what kinde of forme they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly uſe; only it is not much different from a popular State, for they are eſteemed by the number; and are not tranſcended in judgement and worth by the plebeans; and they march to warre not in long rancks, and wedgewiſe-ſquadrons: but in cluſtred and round troopes; nor have they mutinouſly any civill conflicts among themſelves, which in mankinde is both
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:4115:10"/>
mad and horrid, but they encounter and bicker with man himſelfe, whom often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times they conquer triumphantly: nor are they leſſe conſtant in their leagve of of friendſhip with man, nay they ſurpaſſe him in fidelity, for
<q>
                  <l>When the merry ſtore is ſpent,</l>
                  <l>Friends then ſhrink, and do abſent,</l>
                  <l>For all fortunes ſhare not bent:</l>
               </q>
But a <hi>Louce</hi> is a conſtant ſtickler to a man: and neither comes nor goes with fortune; but is cheefly delighted with adverſe (that is yours) fortune; ſo generous and nobly minded he is, for hee is a true companion and attendant to poverty:
<q>
                  <l>It ſhuns the Court and ſtately Gates</l>
                  <l>Of the wealthy Potentates.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore as <hi>Scipio</hi> anciently ſaid, that he was never leſſe at leiſure, then when he was at leiſure: ſo I alſo doe thinke that you (Mendicant Senators) are never leſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, then when you are alone in priſon and chaines: for you have about you per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall and truſty companions, that doe accompany you to the very Gallowes, but
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:4115:11"/>
eſpecially the Crab-lice, which doe take up their ſtation in your Codpiece, Arme-pits, Beards, and Eye-browes: for what place ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer they doe gripingly ſeaze on, they keep their hold untill the laſt gaſpe. Concerning the reſt, it is exceeding wonderfull, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt incredible, what I ſhall tell you; for as famous Authors doe relate, that the great and tutelar gods of the Trojans did abandon the city, upon the Grecians ſack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it: ſo theſe alſo doe when they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive any body marked for death, they pack away by troopes, and this obſeruation ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer failed the wiſeſt Phyſitians and Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers. Whereupon ſome have thought that theſe haue a propheticall faculty in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uining. Beholding the meaſure and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe of their body, you will thinke they are able to atchieue either little, or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but
<q>
                  <l>Reade the renowne and douted deeds of them,</l>
                  <l>And learne the worth of their heroicke ſtem,</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>You will preſently change your opinion, for whether it bee through an ingenious modeſtie, or elſe tooke up with other af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:4115:11"/>
they doe contemne Chronicles, they doe conceale their praiſes and valiant acts, men being neuer the ſorryer for it. <hi>Scylla</hi> the chiefe man of the world, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander of the Romans, who vanquiſht <hi>Marius</hi> twice, and twice <hi>Mithridates,</hi> who diſmantled and ſackt <hi>Athens,</hi> who beſmea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red all <hi>Italy</hi> with ſlaughters: This man, I ſay, they did inuade with troopes; to ſay nothing of <hi>Arnulphus, Antiochus, Herode, Maximinian, Pheretimus, Honorius, Caſſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der:</hi> all Kings and Princes: not deſcending to relate of priuate perſonages, over whom they got moſt illuſtrious victories, incoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring them weaponleſſe and ſouldierleſſe: as that if I have any judgement, my Client may deſervedly challenge, and aſſume to himſelfe this encomiaſticke title out of the Greeke,
<q>
                  <l>I thus a Louce, doe men and Tyrants tame,</l>
                  <l>And of dread <hi>Themis</hi> I a Sergeant am.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>I would have giuen you the Latin, but that <hi>Pediculus,</hi> runs from a Roman verſe; more friendly complying with the Greeks, as he hath reaſon; though he is courteous
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:4115:12"/>
and ſociable enough with others, that hee hath begun the leaſt familiarity with: for he doth not gaſh, nor hurt any one, but onely tickles them, unleſſe whom hee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vades in a troope, wherin (as <hi>Socrates</hi> ſaith in <hi>Plautus Phoedon</hi>) 'tis a queſtion whether it be a greater paine, or pleaſure: but that if there be any paine, it is the progenitor of pleaſure; which dainty kinde of tickling, (my Lords) I thinke you are ſo taken with, as that I imagine, it is your chiefeſt and moſt luſhious reliſhment of your poore and miſerable condition. Often haue I ſeene with what expreſſive delight, you uſe to rubbe and ſcratch, ſometimes your backe, ſometimes your head, ſometimes your ſides, ſometimes another part, to which this your gueſt doth give the gentle itching twitch: for if Pleaſure be as <hi>Plato</hi> ſaith, but a meere repletion, and that riſing from indigencie: I wonder if you can bring any other cauſe of that your ſo mighty fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cative pleaſure, but this your accuſed de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendant, whom (I will tell you a pretty jeſt) by all your ſcratching of your head,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:4115:12"/>
and ſcrubbing of your body, you deſtroy never a whit the more, but multiply him. The Philoſophers can tell you the cauſe hereof. What will you ſay and they prove Chirurgians, for the beſt approved Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians do confeſſe, that it is good to have lice in the head. As for their death, with what wonderfull courage, how undaunted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly do they ſuffer. For many times (being now at deaths doore, ſhaking hands with all the world, and ſcaffoled upon the very comb, the uſuall place of execution, he wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth about ſecurely, without being moved in minde at all; that he might do nought contrary to the dignity of his forepaſſed life, or ſcandalize his credit, whereof no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and brave ſpirits are ever eſpecially cheary. <hi>Augustus Caeſar</hi> is ſaid to have wiſhed for an eaſie departure, and quicke riddance in his death, which this creature (I thinke) onely hath, for he is not martyrd with lingering and chronicall, for with ſmart and acute pangs: hee feeles not the Pleureſie, Stone, or winde-collick, I gueſſe, becauſe at his birth, <hi>Venus</hi> ſtood in the eight
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:4115:13"/>
place from the horoſcope, which as the Mathematicians doe well declare, doth prognoſticate a moſt eaſie and unpaining death to mortals; among whom, our Cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent is not the loweſt in degree. Thus he is gone, but with the turning of a thumbe; herein onely to be lamented, becauſe he ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers undeſervingly, though not therefore the more miſerable, for no man in his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified judgement, can call calamitous in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency, infelicity: which they ſay <hi>Socrates</hi> ſaid alſo before his death, when ſome of his friends did therefore grieve, that ſo good a man as he ſhould ſuffer ſo undeſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vingly. Now the moſt part are extinguiſht with untimely death, and therefore with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Pompe, Shewes, and a Herauld, with a private, not a ſolemne funerall: they are expoſed, rather then repoſed in their tombes, perhaps becauſe they dye in their minority, and before they come to age: wherefore commonly they deceaſe inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate. Theſe are but a few commendations, culled and floſculated out of many: for who dares hope to be able for to diſplay
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:4115:13"/>
them all. Since the top of all knowledge, and oracle of wiſedome, <hi>Homer,</hi> (if the Greekes may bee beleeved) could not unfold the nature of this his perpetuall companion in a riddle:
<q>
                  <l>What we tooke, we left, and what</l>
                  <l>We could not take, we doe bring that.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And overcome with fretting at ſo high a myſterie, fairely made a dye on't. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps it was in juſt judgement too, for ſome doe thinke, that ſome where in his verſes, he ſpake contemptuouſly and unreverent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of his Worſhip: eſpecially the Gramma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians thinkes ſo, which have never ſtood ill affected to this our Client, being his he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditary friends and familiars.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now you Fathers and Peeres of the beging regiment) take all heed hereafter what you do: for if you pleaſe to inflict a penalty on them, you may with a trice confine and baniſh them; for they may bee either gently ſet down to the ground, or elſe in your courteſie they may bee merrily &amp; iudiciouſly beſtowed upon another; where they may live as they did afore, and change nothing but the place; you have exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:4115:14"/>
for it, &amp; reformation in a matter of conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence is never too late. You cannot chuſe but know that the Indians, ever ſince the Gym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſophiſts, have been held the wiſeſt of men, and almoſt the only ſages. It is reported that that there is among them a Bancan nation, ſo named in that part, which now they call Guz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarat, who almoſt only conceiving of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency and endowments of this admirable creature, do cheriſh, harbour, and welcome it, as much as they can. Now as hee is won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully multiplying and increaſing, after that his numerous ofspring is begun to be diffuſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly propogated,</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>Where childrens children thronged be,</l>
                  <l>And their nephewed progeny.</l>
               </q>
               <hi>That nation calleth for a Prieſt out of a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſart, who receiving them with his hallowed hands, putteth them in his head, for their honeſt education. Some when they catch them, lay, and hide them in chincks of wals; and if any one in their preſence do go about to kill them, they make interceſsion with their teares, and prayers, to forbeare ſuch a ſinne in in their ſight: and if all be in vaine, they give
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:4115:14"/>
a golden ranſome for their lives, and pay it down on the nayle. With theſe the wiſeſt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the Iewes do agree, who in their Tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mud or Canon-law, do cenſure the murderer of a Louce on the Sabbath day, and hold it unlawfull to looke for Lice by their Sabbath candels If you never heard of this, now at laſt bee moved, and let your conſcience feele ſome compunction: Be mercifull to them, J adiure you by the ghoſts of their martyred pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſours. Spare your miſerable ſuppliant con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered, coſens and kindred, that are borne of you, that are bred by you, which tend on you, follow you, and adhere to you; which are ready to undergo either fortune with you. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware, leſt you apoſtatize from truth, by idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trizing upon only fancy, or maintaining ſtifly a conceit aggravated with felony.</hi>
            </p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Vivat Pediculus.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
